Guide to the Chasen Gaver papers, 1977-1988
Gaver, Chasen papers, 1977-1988
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Chasen Gaver papers, 1977-1988
7575
Chasen Gaver
7.9 cubic ft.
Correspondence, journals, writings, photographs, videotapes, audiotapes and performance props.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The papers of the "performance poet" Chasen Gaver include personal papers as well as photographs, videotapes and audiotapes; also press materials and articles about him and his work, and announcements of his performances. Also, family photographs and correspondence, personal correspondence, a diary called "Fever Journal," notebooks meticulously charting Gaver's health, and a shadowbox puppet theater used for recitations of Gaver's poem "The Ugly Side of Pretty."
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Charles (Chasen) Gaver, the eldest of three children, was born in 1953 in Wooster, Ohio to Richard and Helen Gaver. After taking a B.A. from The College of Wooster in Ohio, Gaver worked as a per diem paralegal at the Federal Trade Commission in Washington, D.C.
Gaver identified himself foremost as a "performance poet." In 1978 he received one of the first grants awarded to an openly gay artist dealing with gay subject matter from the District of Columbia's Commission on Arts and Humanities. Gaver was also the recipient of larger grants in 1981, 1986, and 1987, which enabled him to collaborate with colleagues as well as to document his performances using photographs and video/audio cassettes. In 1977 Gaver began writing sporadically for The Washington Blade; ten years later his book reviews would become a regular feature. In addition, Gaver wrote novels, essays, plays, poems and short stories, many of which were loosely autobiographical. Gaver's interest in human relationships and his identity as a gay man were common themes in his work.
Although Gaver spent most of his later life in the D.C. area, he made several trips abroad, notably one to Morocco in 1982 where he was introduced to the ex-patriot writer Paul Bowles. Correspondence between Gaver and Bowles dates from 1982-1987.
Gaver was also involved in two organizations; the National Organization for Women (N.O.W.) for which he started a chapter while attending The College of Wooster, and the Washington D.C.-based artists collective Black Artists/White Artists. He also participated in Young Audiences, a performing arts program for inner city children.
In 1987 Gaver was diagnosed with AIDS and began extensively documenting his life with the illness in "Fever Journal," a narrative account including clippings and correspondence from October 1987-June 1988, and the medical notebooks, dated 4/17/87 - 1/31/89 and 2/2/89 - 3/10/89 which listed Gaver's daily food and drug intake as well as his temperature and diminishing body weight. Gaver died of complications due to AIDS in Washington, D.C. in March 1989.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Gaver's work, including "Daddy!," an audiocassette of him reading some of his works in 1978; "Summer Beach Talk," self-published, 1980; "A Book of One Performance," a poetry chapbook, 1980; "From Now Till Doomsday," 1980; and a script for "Standing in the Shadows of Love," performed at the National Theatre, February 2, 1981. Also press materials and articles about him and his work, and announcements of his performances. His 1978 grant from the D.C. Commission on the Arts and Humanities may have been the first grant the Commission awarded to an openly gay artist incorporating gay themes in his artwork.
Also, Chasen Gaver memorial service documents; 13 videos of Gaver's performance poetry; photographs, certificates, audiotapes, publications in which Gaver's work appeared, an autobiographical assemblage of various genres documenting his life and work, letters, and publicity photographs. Family photographs and correspondence, personal correspondence, a diary called "Fever Journal," notebooks meticulously charting Gaver's health, and a shadowbox puppet theater used for recitations of Gaver's poem "The Ugly Side of Pretty." Includes correspondence with Paul Bowles.
Includes correspondence to Gregory Ford after Chasen's death, including statements affirming and celebrating Chasen's life. Also, information commemorating him at the College of Wooster (Ohio); "Outline for discussion with Millie Cravedi and Pam Layng re: 'Death' 5/29/88" (a planned discussion of death with several friends). Also, poems, a literary resume, and photographs of Gaver and friends.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Gaver, Chasen.; Bowles, Paul, 1910-; Ford, Gregory.; Cravedi, Millie.; Layng, Pam.; Byron, Judy.; District of Columbia.--Commission on the Arts and Humanities.; House of Color.
Subjects:
Gay's writings.; Poetry.; Gays.; AIDS (Disease).
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videocassettes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
PROVENANCE
Collection donated by Gregory Ford, lover of Chasen Gaver.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Personal,
Boxes 1, 4, 6, 7, 12, 17
Chasen Gaver's personal papers include a scrapbook compiled by Gregory Ford, Chasen's lover and donor of his papers, literary resumes, publicity for his performances, an ink drawing of him by Judy Byron, a passport, award certificates, an address book, an Alcoholic Anonymous coin, a will, obituaries, and programs and statements from "A Darker Pair of Glasses," a posthumous tribute to Gaver by his friends and lovers.
Series II. Correspondence
Boxes 1, 17, 19, 20
Gaver's correspondence dates from 1974-1989 and includes letters to and from friends and family, and business letters concerning his work. Clippings and personal writings filed amongst the correspondence have been retained as have Gaver's original folder titles. Prominently featured in this series are letters from Judy Byron, an artist with whom Gaver collaborated; Gaver's "muse," official photographer, and long time friend Emillie (Millie, Drag, Paco Caliente) Cravedi whom Gaver met in 1976; and Paul Bowles for whom Gaver performed a poem in Tangier, Morocco in 1982. Gaver also received a picture of the designer Halston, autographed by Andy Warhol.
Series III. Writings
Boxes 1, 2, 4, 5, 6, 9-11, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21
This series includes unpublished manuscripts, published poetry anthologies, poetry drafts, journals, book reviews, short stories, screenplays, poetry/video scripts and privately printed chapbooks of Gaver's poetry. Gaver occasionally wrote under the pseudonym Gloria de la Calle and this is reflected in several anthologies. He was also affiliated with Dirt and Rats magazine to which he often contributed material. Notable is Gaver's "Fire Book," a thirteen-year journal which traces the evolution of the gay liberation/ women's movements of the 1970's in conjunction with Gaver's performance career. His "Fever Journal" and medical notebooks are found in this series.
Series IV. Photographs
Boxes 7, 8, 13, 15, 17, 20
This series documents Gaver's life in the 1970's, through the height of his performance career in the 1980's, to his untimely death in early March 1989. Gaver's friends from the 1970's and 1980's and his performances (documented by Emillie Cravedi and Ken Goggin) figure prominently. Also included are family photographs from the 1960's, and individual photographs of Gaver with Bella Abzug, Effie Barry, and the members of Black Artists/White Artists as well as slides from Gaver's memorial service and photographs of Gaver's AIDS quilt panel.
Series V. Miscellany
Boxes 2, 3, 4, 5, 7, 14, 15, 20, Mapcase Folder 1
This series includes files Gaver kept on varied topics such as Black Artists/White Artists, the National Theatre, Young Audiences, grant proposals, and cassette tape production. Also included is a poetry anthology which contains work by Mecca Rylance an admirer of Gaver, duplicates of photographs and other printed material, and two props used in conjunction with Gaver's performances.
Series VI.Audio/Video
Box 16
This series includes cassette and video recordings of Gaver's poetry readings and performances. Descriptive notes for audio tapes tr6945a-tr6947a, tr6962a, and tr6979a can be found in Box 2, folder 23. Please see the attached audio/video description list for additional information.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Personal
  - Drawing of Chasen Gaver by Judy Byron (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Literary resumes (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Literary resumes (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Passports (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alcoholics Anonymous coin (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Awards (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Obituaries and memorial service program (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "A Darker Pair of Glasses," tribute to Gaver by friends and lovers (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Address book (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gaver publicity (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Out, Gaver featured on cover (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gaver publicity (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Matted picture of Gaver on cover of Out (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Award from the Federal Trade Commission to Gaver for contributions on handling confidentiality and disclosure laws, 1987 (Box 7)
  - "The Party's Over" artwork by Gaver, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Judy Byron and Gaver publicity (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Gaver's will (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook compiled by Gregory Ford (Box 12)
  - Postcards and souvenirs from trip to Greece, July 1986 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Handmade buttons (Keith Haring illustration, Willi Smith photo, Pee Wee Herman [a.k.a. Paul Reubens] photo), postcard with photo titled "Apparitions to Americans: I" (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - "Important Correspondence", 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Important Correspondence", 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Important Correspondence", 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Important Correspondence", 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Important Correspondence", 1974-1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Paul Bowles correspondence, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Patricia Harris correspondence (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Mayor Marion Barry correspondence (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence with "Donald" (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Gregory Ford correspondence, 1981-1984 (Box 19, Folder 13-14)
  - Professional correspondence (Box 20, Folder 34)
- Series III. Writings
  - Medical notebook, April 17, 1987-January 31, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Medical notebook, February 2-March 10, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Fever journal", October 1987-June 1988 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Fever journal", October 1987-June 1988 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - "Miscellaneous items from journal" (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Miscellaneous items from journal" (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Mykonos" (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Journal entries (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Black Light, includes essay by Gaver (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - New Blood, Alternative Fiction and Poetry, includes poems by Gaver (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Garden State, includes poem by Gaver (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - The Gay Alternative, includes essay by Gaver (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Crash Pads," chapter 1 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Crash Pads," chapter 2:'The Ice Palace' (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Crash Pads," chapter 3: 'Mud Huts' (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Crash Pads," chapter 4: 'Beatniques' (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Idea" (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Pre-War" (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Put Your Hands on Your Head... (Simon Sez)" (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "August" (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "O' Solo" (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "O' Solo" (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Lifeguard" (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Standing in the Shadows of Love" (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Contrabutions" [sic] (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Omnipotence's Flower Garden (Blessing Unwarranted)" (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Short stories (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Emillie Cravedi's Refrigerator (a sequential collection of short stories and connecting paragraphs)" (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Drafts of essays and reviews (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reviews for The Washington Blade, December 1977-January 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Articles and reviews (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Published poetry (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Tunnel Vision" (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Tables," a one act play (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Desk in Hell," a video play (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Fresh Out of Ideas," a video poem (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Fun," a screenplay, January-May 1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "Personality Cult," a poetry cassette script (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Poetry miscellany (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Dirt magazine reunion (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Straight/White/Male, includes essay by Gaver (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Whose Woods These Are, includes poem by Gaver (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Articles by Gaver from greater Philadelphia area (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Impressions, Volume 5, includes poem by Gaver, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Party's Over, book by Gaver (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Fennel Stalk, includes poem by Gaver, Winter 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Mouth of the Dragon, includes poems by Gaver, June 1975 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lip Service, Volume 1, Number 1, includes poems by Gaver, Spring/Fall 1987 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Dirt, includes articles by Gaver, Fall 1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Dirt, Volume 3, Issue 1, includes poem and stories by Gaver, Summer 1980 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Dirt, includes poems by Gaver, Spring 1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Dirt, Volume 5, Issue 1, includes poem and article by Gaver, Summer 1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Chapbook, "A Book of One Performance" (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Chapbook, "From Now Til Doomsday" (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Chapbook, "Summer Beach Talk" (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Poetry and articles (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "Fire Book" (Box 9)
  - "Orange and Blue", January 15, 1985-May 30, 1987 (Box 10)
  - "Lightning", July 1, 1988-January 27, 1989 (Box 11)
  - "The Party's Over" uncompleted page proofs and illustrations (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - "The Party's Over" page proofs (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
  - Dirt, page proofs, contains poem and article by Gaver, Winter 1980 (Box 18, Folder 3-4)
  - Stencils, used in illustrations for "The Party's Over" (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Narrative to "Fire Books" (original) (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - "Armed 'Camp'" (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - "Too REEL for Hollywood" (Box 19, Folder 3-4)
  - "Love-a-dub-dub" (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - "Bizarre is in the Eye of the Beholder" (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - "You Too Can Save the President" (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - "WA lnut 2- 1939" (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - "Wet Paint" (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - "Try-Fling" (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - "MISS-Elaneous" (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - "poly-tic-tic-tick..." (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Published work (partial) (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - "Don't Panic," "An Enduring Relationship," "#42" (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - "Souvenirs" (Box 19, Folder 17-18)
  - "Wild/Life" (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - "In Sickness and In Health" (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - "Temper, Temper" (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "Air Tight" (Box 20, Folder 4-5)
  - "This Just In" (Box 20, Folder 6-7)
  - "Fresh Out of Ideas" (Box 20, Folder 8-9)
  - "Goody-Goody-Goody" (Box 20, Folder 10-11)
  - "Give the Dancers Castanets" (Box 20, Folder 12-13)
  - "Make It!" (Box 20, Folder 14-15)
  - "Natural Causes" (Box 20, Folder 16-17)
  - "No Surprises!" (Box 20, Folder 18-19)
  - "Any Excuse to Go Out" (Box 20, Folder 20-21)
  - "So-So-Systematic" (Box 20, Folder 22-24)
  - "Do More For Me!" (Box 20, Folder 25-26)
  - "Separate Vacations" (Box 20, Folder 27-28)
  - "Peekaboo!" (Box 20, Folder 29-30)
  - "Tunnel Vision" (Box 20, Folder 31-33)
  - Index of Writing (Box 20, Folder 34)
  - Untyped poems (Box 20, Folder 35)
  - Unfinished poems (Box 20, Folder 36)
  - "Terms" (for use in poems) (Box 20, Folder 37)
  - "Part III: Peak Seasons" (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - "Part IV: Social Change" (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - "Later..." (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Poems (Box 21, Folder 4-15)
- Series IV. Photographs
  - Photo album (friends and family), 1970s (Box 15)
  - Gaver, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Gaver with parents, c. 1955 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Gaver and father (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Gaver's mother, Helen Gaver, c. 1970s (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Gaver with family, c. 1969 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Pamela (Chasen's sister) and Steve Somers with sons Joel and Bryan (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Gaver with sisters Pamela and Jill, 1980s (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Gaver with Emillie Cravedi, c. 1980 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Negatives of Gaver with Emillie Cravedi, c. 1980 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Booklet of Gaver publicity photos, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Gaver with Marion Barry, c. 1980's (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Gaver with Effi Barry (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Autographed photo of Bella Abzug given to Gaver (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Gaver and Judy Byron (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Gaver with Black Artists/White Artists members (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Quilt and "skinny pix" negatives, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Slides from Gaver's memorial service (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Photo album, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Photo album, c. 1975 (Box 7)
  - Photo album, c. 1975 (Box 7)
  - Photo album, c. 1975 (Box 7)
  - Family photographs, 1970's (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Family photographs, 1970's, 1980's (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Family photographs, 1970's, 1980's (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Millie Cravedi (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "Publicity for GW performances and Out", c. 1970's (Box 13, Folder 5-11)
  - Performances, c. 1978-1981 (Box 13, Folder 12-19)
  - Gay and Lesbian Pride, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 20-22)
  - "Publicity, Boston", 1984 (Box 13, Folder 23-29)
  - Joker,' 'I'm One too,' 'Spy Phone,' 'Cat's Cradle,' 'Boston 1984', 1984 (Box 13, Folder 30-34)
  - "Ritz photos, Boston session", December 1984 (Box 13, Folder 35-38)
  - "Ken Goggin 1984", 1984 (Box 13, Folder 39-41)
  - Greece, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 42-45)
  - "Publicity: fiorucci glasses, skull, microphone" (Box 13, Folder 46-49)
  - "Publicity: airplane, fiorucci glasses, scarf, empire state" (Box 13, Folder 50-53)
  - "Herb's performance, 20009's by Jim Marks" (Box 13, Folder 54-58)
  - "Boston #1", April 1986 (Box 13, Folder 59-64)
  - "Stay or Go #1", April 1986 (Box 13, Folder 65-68)
  - "Stay or Go #3", April 1986 (Box 13, Folder 69-70)
  - "Publicity: airplane, fiorucci glasses, scarf, empire state" (Box 13, Folder 71-74)
  - "Publicity", March 1987 (Box 13, Folder 75-81)
  - "March 1987", March 1987 (Box 13, Folder 82-87)
  - Gaver's AIDS quilt panel (outdoors) (Box 13, Folder 88-90)
  - Gaver's AIDS quilt panel (indoors) (Box 13, Folder 91-94)
  - "Skinny pix," Gaver with AIDS at 88 lbs., February 1989 (Box 13, Folder 95-97)
  - Photos and negatives of apartment; photo of Gaver in "Beat: The Performance Poetry of Chasen Gaver" (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - "Arlington Arts Opening", January 1988 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Gaver on telephone; cars through rainy windshield (Box 20, Folder 38)
  - Negatives of Gaver by Emillie Cravedi, Daniel Cima, Rick Reinhart, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Negatives of Gaver by Emillie Cravedi, Daniel Cima, Rick Reinhart, 1975-1980 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Negatives of Gaver by Emillie Cravedi, Daniel Cima, Rick Reinhart, 1975-1984 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Negatives of Gaver by Emillie Cravedi, Daniel Cima, Rick Reinhart, 1984-1986 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Negatives of Gaver by Emillie Cravedi, Daniel Cima, Rick Reinhart, 1986-1988 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Series V. Miscellany
  - WPA Document, 1986 (Folder 1)
  - Audiocassette inserts from "Downtown Details" (tr6945a); "Confession"/ "BeHe" (tr6946a); "Last Supper" (tr6947a); "Boston Tape" (tr6962a); and "In Common" (tr6979a). (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Planet Detroit, an anthology of urban poetry (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Out, April and June 1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Permissions and private funds for "Watershed" tapes (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Washington, D.C. Arts Grant, 1978, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous grant proposals, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Expense notebook including grant receipts, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Jumping to Conclusions cassette", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Photo session concepts", 1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "National Theatre" (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Young Audiences" (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Black Artists/White Artists" (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Black Artists/White Artists Journal January 1988" (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Medical miscellany (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Shaman," poem given to Gaver from friend (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Artwork by Emillie Cravedi (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Andy Warhol autographed map mentioning Halston (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Andy Warhol autographed picture of Halston (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Black scarf worn in Gaver's performances (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Clown puppet prop used in "Ugly Side of Pretty" (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Copyright registration certificates (Box 20, Folder 34)
  - "Miscellaneous items from journal" (original) [ RESTRICTED] (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Whose Woods These Are (duplicate) [ RESTRICTED] (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Out (duplicates) [ RESTRICTED] (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - "Louis' Eviction," from The Washington Review, 1980 (duplicates) [ RESTRICTED] (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Photo duplicates [ RESTRICTED] (Box 16, Folder 5-21)
- Series VI. Audio/Video
  - Video Tapes
  - "'Beat: The Performance Poetry of Chasen Gaver,' a video by Jamie Walter.", V-138; Interviews with Craig Gibson, E. Ethelbert Miller, Gideon Ferebee, Emilie Cravedi and others.
  - "Beat Interviews, Cravedi; Lenny; Jamie (Chasen's copy)", V-139; In a mock interview, Gaver and Cravedi recount their meeting and subsequent friendship, politics, and collaborative performances ending in a performance of "Ma Cheer." Gaver and "Lenny" discuss Dirt magazine. Gaver and Jamie Walters discuss the relation between video and performance poetry and Dirt magazine.
  - Duplicate of V-139, V-140
  - "Performance pastiche/'Beat' Demo" (title on label); "Performance Pastiche: The Collaborations of Jack Guidone" (title on video), V-141
  - "Performance/Singing for The Party's Over book party 10/12/85, Edes House", October 12, 1985; V-142; Includes performance poetry by Chasen Gaver from The Party's Over as well as readings and speeches from friends.
  - "Fresh Out of Ideas" (1984), "Under Suspicion" (1984), "Desk in Hell" (1982), "Jackie Strikes Back," "Louise takes a Bath," "The Dishes," "The Boat", 1982, 1984; V-143; Performance poetry by Gaver and friends.
  - "Assault with a Deadly Rhythm," "Disappearing Act", V-144; "Disappearing Act" was written by Chasen Gaver and performed by Larry Duckette. "Assault with a Deadly Rhythm" is a music video by Ground Zero with which Gaver was not associated.
  - "A Darker Pair of Glasses", April 9, 1990; V-145; A tribute to Chasen Gaver's life and work performed by his friends at the National Theatre, Washington, D.C. Includes excerpts from "O'Solo," and speeches and performances by friends and lovers, i.e., Emillie Cravedi, Gregory Ford, Craig Gibson.
  - "Original of 'Stay or Go?' Ferebee/Gaver", August 17, 1986; V-146; A collaborative performance of poetry by Chasen Gaver and Gideon Ferebee, funded in part by the National Endowment for the Arts. Taped before a live audience at the En Marge Gallery
  - "Performance Poet Chasen Gaver in 'New Colors,' Washington, D.C.", March 17, 1985; V-147; Gaver performing poetry in a video by Perry Fitzhugh.
  - Duplicate of V-147, V-148
  - "Perry Fitzhugh's Starcissm, Prince, 20009, Political Climate, Then What", February 1, 1986; V-149
  - "What Can a Poem Do? with Chasen Gaver", V-150; Gaver performing poetry in a video directed by David Scott.
  - "AIDS Interview with Chasen Gaver", July 1988; V-188; An interview in which Gaver discusses how AIDS has affected his life and relationships.
  - Audio Tapes
  - La Layng, July 4, 1987; tr6930a
  - Sounds, tr6931a
  - Sounds for "Stay or Go", tr6932a
  - Sounds from Adrian X-mas, December 1986; tr6933a
  - Sounds, tr6934a
  - Al Bell (side A); Dif'rent Strokes - Gay Rights 3/20/77 (side B), c. March 1977; tr6935a
  - Akron, May 1986; tr6936a
  - Bette's Comedy Album 8/84 (side A); Bideon Ferebee 6/14/84 and Cinque 8/2/84 WPFW (side B), June, August 1984; tr6937a
  - About it, tr6938a